So the first step of problem solving might sound really simple.
It's around defining the problem.
So what is defining the problem, you might say?
And though it sounds really simple, it's actually…
articulating what it is that you're trying to solve
through the course of the problem-solving exercise.
It actually is probably one of the most challenging steps
of the problem-solving approach, for a number of reasons.
The first is because everybody actually might see
the problem a little bit differently.
So getting clarity on what it is that you're actually solving
is really paramount.
Another reason is because people might have different ways that they're defining success
in what the problem is aimed to solve.
In other words, what does successfully solving
the problem actually look like?
So articulating and aligning around the core problem and what success looks like is one
of the fundamental steps — but actually much more tricky than it might initially appear.
And so, Marc, maybe — what does that look like
in day-to-day life for you?
I think it can vary, and define the problem
in terms of the time frame, but
I'll just give an example. If you're introducing a new product
and you're trying to think about how you price it,
initially that could sound like a relatively defined problem:
what's the price for this product?
But actually, different people could be thinking about it in different ways.
Are you pricing it to gain adoption? Are you pricing it to maximize profits?
And so actually being very clear on what the problem is you're trying to solve,
and getting alignment, can be absolutely critical.
So in defining the problem, it also occurs at different periods of time.
In a larger project, you may have really spent the time, hopefully, up front
to define what that is and have alignment. But sometimes, if there's a shorter duration —
a couple of weeks, a couple of days, or even in the moment —
it's those times where you may take for granted
that everyone knows what the problem you're trying to solve is.
But those can actually be the times when it's most useful to stop and ask yourself, ask the people
you're working with: are we aligned on the problem we're trying to solve together?
It's interesting about making decisions and problem solving in the moment,
because there's actually different types of in-the-moment decisions.
There are those that are in an urgent crisis mode in the moment.
And then there are those sort of ad hoc decisions that you have to make
with high frequency, but perhaps lower consequences.
I find the first group actually particularly interesting, because in those moments
it's high intensity, high stress, high urgency.
One of the examples that I often think about is one of our clients —
the CEO of a cruise line — called at 3 a.m. in the morning
because they had suffered a series of pretty significant catastrophes
on their cruise liners. And as a result,
we were called at three in the morning to help them
solve this very important, pressing problem.
And very quickly it dawned on us
that we were all unclear about what this was.
Was it about saving the lives of people
who might be endangered or hurt in the incidents?
Or was it about getting them back in operation as quickly as possible,
so more people could enjoy the experience of a wonderful cruise?
Or was it about restoring the reputation
that this institution had built over many generations?
Really honing in on what the “what” was, was critical at the first step —
because, as you could imagine, the solutions for all those different
questions were fundamentally different.
So I can really relate to that. I think, particularly in the moment,
there are two challenges that we oftentimes see.
One is you are oftentimes dealing with imperfect information. It's in the moment;
you haven't had time to do analysis. So what do you do in that moment?
I think the second is, particularly for those urgent situations,
there's such a strong bias to action
that sometimes the hardest thing to do is to force yourself and force the group to stop and think
and say, “Hey, have we actually defined this problem as best we can?”
So we can get to the answer of what we're trying to solve.